A Guide to the Publications of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1947-1997
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #Z 1008 .V54
Publications of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1947-1997 1947-1997
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
Z 1008 .V54
ca. 200 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content
In at least one sense bibliography did not begin at home for the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, for the Society has never maintained a complete list of its own publications. The fullest record of what in fact has been the Society's chief activity in its first half-century can be found in the annual listings published in
Studies in Bibliography
, beginning with its initial volume. A number of other sources help to amplify that history. In 1979, stimulated by a gift of Society publications from William B. O'Neal, a former councilor of the Society, the Rare Book Department of the University of Virginia Library attempted to gather all such books and pamphlets and thereby establish a formal record of them; this collection is important as a focused attempt to provide a comprehensive account, but it falls short of completeness even for the first thirty years of the Society, and it was never developed for subsequent ones. For at least half of its life the Society has maintained a card file listing its productions, while the volumes the Society has accumulated in its office have over the years assumed the status of a reference collection and sometimes provide the sole evidence of an item's existence. The collections of individuals likewise prove to be important resources for piecing together the Society's work as a publisher; these in turn are indebted to booksellers particularly those in Charlottesville, who are foremost in recycling the accumulations of early Society members. Some documentary materials about the publications also exist: sporadic holdings of invoices and correspondence in Society files, references in the
Secretary's News Sheet
or in irregular runs of Society minutes, and the papers of the Society's chief founders. Linton Massey's records were conveyed to the Society on his demise; the Society materials that John Cook Wyllie and Fredson Bowers had in their possession at the time of their deaths passed with other papers to the Special Collections Department of the University Library(thus accounting for the presence of one of the Society's ledger books there instead of with the others in the Society office). It is appropriate that a record of a bibliographical society's publications therefore depends on representatives of its chief constituencies: private and institutional collectors, individual scholars and scholarly organizations, archivists, and booksellers.
In the following list, two major series, the
Secretary's News Sheet
and
Studies in Bibliography
, are listed separately from the Society's other publications. Because the
News Sheet
is not widely known and has not been covered by indexes, I have noted those contents that have general bibliographical interest. The News Sheets that were devoted to a single topic were sometimes sold separately (and frequently appear in book dealers' catalogs without identification as part of the series); I have listed these both with the
News Sheets
, where the fuller information appears, and with the general publications. Especially during its first decade the Society made available to members various items which technically were not its own productions. Some of these bear such a close connection to the Society, however, that they merit inclusion; accordingly, they have been alphabetized with the other entries for the appropriate years (1947, 1949, 1952, and 1965), but they have been enclosed by braces. Unless otherwise indicated, the publications are hardbound, without dust jackets. Paperbound publications are described as in "covers" (that is, separate pieces of paper, usually thick) or in "wrappers" (a single piece of paper, occasionally thick, continuous around the spine).
In its first fifty years the Society has produced 53 issues of its
Secretary's News Sheet
, 50 volumes of
Studies in Bibliography
(and reprints of 20 of them), and about 175 other publications. Though the amount of information available about the items varies, what is recoverable from archives and from the publications themselves makes clear the way in which the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia has contributed to intellectual life in the second half of the twentieth century and why during that time the name Virginia became an international codeword for bibliographical study.
List
- Secretary's News Sheet
  - (March 1947). 2 pp., 1
    Includes summary of Fredson Bowers's talk "Some Problems and Practices in Bibliographical Descriptions of Modern Authors" on 26 February 1947. Attachments: Constitution (2 pp.); by-laws (1 p.); roster of members as of 15 March 1947 (2 pp.); sample bibliographical descriptions by Bowers (see 1947.1).
  - (May 1947). 3 pp., 2
    Includes summary of Charles D. Hurt's talk "The Monotype" on 18 April 1947. Attachments: "A List of Books Presented to the University through the Bibliographical Society" (1 p.); sample of monotype and linotype settings by Hurt (1 p.).
  - (June 1947). 1 p., 3
    Attachment: "A Note on Linotype Typographic Refinements" (4 pp.); "Why 79 First Folios?" by Charlton Hinman (see 1947.2).
  - (October 1947). 2 pp., 4
    Includes an emendation, by John C. Tarr, of the discussion of monotype in
    Secretary's News Sheet
    2.
  - (December 1947). 2 pp., 5
  - (January 1948). 1 p., 6
  - (June 1948). 2 pp., 7
    Includes announcement of the first volume of the Society's
    Papers
    . Attachment: "Table of Contents for the First Volume of the Papers.. ." (2 pp.).
  - (September 1948). 1 p., 8
  - (March 1949). 3 pp., 9
    Includes an amendment to the Society's constitution. Attachment: President's Report for 1948 (2 pp.).
  - (October 1949). 2 pp., 10
  - (December 1949). 3 pp., 11
  - (January 1950). 3 pp., 12
    Includes "The First Presses in Each of the United States" (Rollo G. Silver).
  - (February 1950). 2 pp., 13
    Includes announcement of Thomas W. Streeter's gift of railroading books to the University Library. Attachments: President's and Treasurer's reports for 1949 (2 pp., 1 p.).
  - (July 1950). 4 pp., 14
    Includes errata for
    Studies in Bibliography
    2 (pp. 72, 74); addenda to "Verner's Checklist of the Separate Editions of Jefferson's
    Notes
    " (Lawrence Wroth, Frederick Goff, and other members; see 1950.5). Attachment: "Addenda & Corrigenda to Morrison's STC Index.. ." (1 p.; see 1950.3).
  - (November 1950). 5 pp., 15
    Includes addenda to "Verner's Checklist of
    Notes on the State of Virginia
    " (Thomas W. Streeter; see 1950.5); "Flatbush Publishing, 1809"; "American Press Numbers"; and "Coxe's Carolana."
  - (February 1951). 4 pp., 16
    Includes addenda to "Verner's Checklist of the Separate Editions of Jefferson's Notes" (see 1950.5); "Evans Addenda" (see 1962.2); "Addenda to McKerrow
    Printers' & Publishers' Devices
    "; "Notes on STC Books"; "Notes on Wing."
  - (March 1951). 4 pp., 17
    Includes "Barney Chesnick Lays a Jefferson Ghost" (concerning
    Notes on Virginia
    see 1950.5); "Notes on STC Books"; "[Donald] Wing Additions to Wing"; "[Walter] Goldwater Additions to Wing"; "Argentine Book Trade."
  - (July 1951). 5 pp., 18
    Includes "James Madison's Books on the Fine Arts" (William B. O'Neal); "Jefferson Notes: Holdings not Previously Recorded" (see 1950.5); "STC Additions" (Allen T. Hazen); "Wing Additions" (John Alden; name corrected in
    20 from "John Crow"). Attachment: Financial report for 1950-51 (1 p.)
  - (September 1951). 3 pp., 19
    Includes "Note on the Mikado" and "Additions to Evans" (see 1962.2).
  - (March 1952). 4 pp., 20
    Includes "A Note on the Binding of the First Edition of Huckleberry Finn" (Walter Harding); "American Wood Engravers" (Raymond Evans); "A Jain Manuscript of the 10th? Century" (S. R. Ranganathan); "English Rare Book Market 1951" (Leona Rostenberg and Madeleine B. Stern); and "Mikado Again" (Joseph R. Dunlap). Attachment: Financial report for 1951-52 (1 p.).
  - (April 1952). 3 pp., 21
    Includes "Press Figure Variants in Cook's Third Voyage, London, 1784."
  - (June 1952). 5 pp., 22
    Includes "Principia Census" (Henry P. Macomber) and "STC Addenda."
  - (July 1952). 10 pp., 23
    List of members (supplement follows in
    24).
  - (October 1952). 7 pp., 24
    Includes "Thomas Paine Collectors" (Col. Richard Gimbel); "Stendhalia in Grenoble" (John Roberson); "STC Addenda"; and additions and corrections to list of members in
    23.
  - (November 1952). 3 pp., 25
    Includes "Frank Norris Manuscripts"; "English Printed Dustjacket on an American Manufactured Book"; and "A Late Revision in Thoreau's `Walden'" (Walter Harding).
  - (February 1953). 4 pp., 26
    Includes "Headline as Footline" and "Wing Addenda."
  - (July 1953). 4 pp., 27
    Includes "Bristol Addendum [to
    Maryland Imprints]
    " (Roger Bristol; see 1953.1); "Corrections for Morrison [
    STC
    Index]" (Charles C. Mish); and "Evans Addenda & Corrigenda" (see 1962.2; "The following notes... were made in the process of preparing the preliminary cards for the forthcoming Index to the
    of the Bibliographical Society of America").
  - (September 1953). 4 pp., 28
    Includes "American Imprints Inventories"; "Evans Addenda & Corrigenda" (see 1962.2); and "Wing Addenda and Corrigenda."
  - (October 1953). 4 pp., 29
    Includes "A Twentieth Century `Stylus'" (Donald Tanasoca); "Wing Addenda & Corrigenda"; "Bristol Addenda [to
    Maryland Imprints
    ] Continued" (Roger Bristol; see 1953.1); and "Books on Printers' Ornaments in the Library of the University of Virginia" (Lucy Clark).
  - (February 1954). 8 pp., 30
    Includes "Bodoni Census" (Robert Frederick Lane); "Wing Addenda" (Walter Goldwater); "Bristol Addenda [to
    ] Continued" (Roger Bristol; see 1953.1); and "Tanasoca Footnote [to article in
    29]" (James Edward Tobin).
  - (October 1954). 16 pp., 31
    Includes "Check-List of Editions of William Wirt's The Letters of the British Spy" (B. Randolph Wellford) and "STC Addenda."
  - (February 1955). 16 pp., 32
    Includes "Non-Recorded Evans Items in the Peabody Institute Library" and "Other Evans Addenda" (Roger P. Bristol; see 1962.2), and "STC Addenda" (W. A. Jackson).
  - (June 1955). 16 pp., 33
    Includes "Wing Addenda"; illustrations of early dust jackets in the Taylor Collection of American Fiction in the University Library; and "A Rich Store of Southern Tall Tales" (Derek Colville).
  - (October 1955). 16 pp., 34
    Includes "James Joyce: Books and Pamphlets Relating to the Author and His Works" (James F. Spoerri; supplements follow in
    37, 42, 48, 51); "Southern Tall Tales [addendum to
    33]" (Lawrence S. Thompson); "Dust Jackets [corrigendum to
    33]"; "Wing Addenda" (Albert E. Lownes); and "Bristol Addenda [to
    ] Continued" (Roger Bristol; see 1953.1). Cover drawing of Joyce by John Canaday, adopted from Augustus John.
  - (September 1956). 8 pp., 35
  - (June 1957). 8 pp., 36
    Includes "Wing Addenda and Corrigenda" (George W. Williams and W. T. Brennan).
  - (September 1957). 16 pp., 37
    Includes: "James Joyce: Books and Pamphlets Relating to the Author and His Works" (James F. Spoerri; supplement to
    34); "Wing Addenda" [Walter Goldwater]; "Harper Records" (John Cook Wyllie); "Correction to News Sheet No. 36 [3.13]"; "Evans Corrigenda" (Roger Bristol; see 1962.2); and "Evans Addenda" (see 1962.2).
  - (February 1958). [8] pp., 38
    Includes "S.T.C. Addenda" (Irvin B. Horst) and "Evans Addenda" (Lawrence Thompson; see 1962.2).
  - (March 1958). Kerlan, Irvin. A Roger Duvoisin Bibliography. 16 pp., 39
    Blue-gray printed wrappers. "The wrap-around cover is a self-portrait of Roger Duvoisin drawn especially for this issue."
  - (September 1958). Lester, John A., Jr. John Davidson: A Grub Street Bibliography. 30 pp., 40
    Blue-gray printed wrappers; front cover has portrait of Davidson "from a contemporary woodcut" and imprint "University of Virginia Press."
  - (February 1959). [8] pp., 41
  - (August 1959). Spoerri, James F. James Joyce: Books and Pamphlets Relating to the Author and His Works. [8] pp., 42
    Supplement to
    34, 37. Cover portrait of Joyce from
    34, but now without wording.
  - (September 1959). O'Neal, William B. A Checklist of Writings on Thomas Jefferson as an Architect. 18 pp., 43
    Blue-gray printed wrappers.
  - (February 1960). 4 pp., 44
  - (April 1960). Gross, Seymour L. Eudora Welty: A Bibliography of Criticism and Comment. 32 pp., 45
  - (June 1960). De Bellis, Jack. An Andrew Nelson Lytle Check List. 15 pp., 46
  - (March 1961). [8] pp., 47
  - (June 1962). [8] pp., 48
    Includes "James Joyce: Books and Pamphlets Relating to the Author and His Works" (James F. Spoerri; supplement to
    34, 37, 42); "An Addition to Secretary's News Sheet, No. 45, p. 1 [Welty checklist]" (George W. Williams).
  - (June 1963). [4] pp., 49
  - (July 1963). O'Neal, William B. Charles Smith: His Work in Book Design: A Checklist. 13, [2] pp., 50
    Blue-gray printed wrappers. "The frontispiece is a zinc line etching of a pen-and-ink sketch by Reginald Marsh. The composition (in Linotype and foundry Baskerville) and makeup were done at the University of Virginia Printing Office, as were the presswork and binding of a 200-copy edition on Strathmore Pastelle with Curtis Tweedweave cover, and a 1000-copy edition on Warren's 1854 with Ticonderoga Laid Text cover. The latter will appear as Secretary's
    News Sheet
    No. 50 of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia [and is identified as such inside the front cover]. A special edition of 25 copies was printed at The Cockescraw Press on Arches mould- made heavyweight text and Fabriano mould-made cover."
  - (February 1964). 8 pp., 51
    34, 37, 42, 48).
  - (August 1966). Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography [Part 1]. 32 pp., 52
    Items located in the process of checking fascicles of Roger P. Bristol's supplement to Evans (1962.2) by librarians and collectors.
  - (December 1967). Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography [Part 2]. [24] pp., 53
    A continuation of the supplement in
    52; see 1962.2.
- Studies in Bibliography
  - (1948-49); as Papers of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia. Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1948. [2], 204, [3] pp., 1
    Stiff paper wrappers. "One thousand copies of this volume have been printed in December 1948 at the William Byrd Press in Richmond, Virginia, under the supervision of Willis Shell, one of the Society's charter members. The text is set in Monotype Garamont, a face designed by Frederic W. Goudy for the Lanston Monotype Machine Company of Philadelphia in 1920. The type face was drawn from the 16th century designs of Claude Garamond, and named for the Latin form of the Frenchman's name. The type for the book was keyboarded by Captain Horace F. Webb and cast by Allen H. Kelly. The hand composition was by S. Frank Spencer, and C. Raymond Brown, the presswork by James W. and Raymond E. Knight. The paper is Strathmore Pastelle Text. The binding is by Meister & Smethie and the William Byrd Press." Reprint: As
    Studies in Bibliography: Papers of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia
    . Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, October 1964. Plate facing 185 printed as 184; list of bookdealers' catalogues (original p. 205) omitted and subsequent pages moved up. 516 copies. Electronic edition: see 1997.3.
  - (1949-50); as Studies in Bibliography: Papers of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia (sub-title continuing through vol. 24). Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1949. [4], 213, [1] pp., 2
    Stiff paper wrappers. "The second volume of the Bibliographical Society Papers, Studies In Bibliography was set in Monotype Garamont and printed on Strathmore Pastelle Text and Curtis Tweedweave Cover. Designing, composition and presswork were by the William Byrd Press, Inc. of Richmond, Virginia. The binding was done by L. H. Jenkins, Inc. of Richmond. One thousand copies were printed and bound." Reprint: Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, October 1964. List of bookdealers' catalogues (original pp. 210-211) omitted and subsequent pages moved up and repaginated. 541 copies. Electronic edition: see 1997.3.
  - (1950-51). Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1950. [4], 306, [1] pp., 3
    Stiff paper wrappers. Errata slip for Miller article tipped in before half-title. "The third volume of the Bibliographical Society Papers,
    Studies In Bibliography
    , was set in Monotype Garamont and printed on Strathmore Pastelle Text and Curtis Tweedweave Cover. Designing, composition, presswork, sewing and placing in wrappers, were by the William Byrd Press, Inc. of Richmond, Virginia. One thousand copies were manufactured." The final two lines on the title-page verso were printed after the rest of the sheet. Reprint: Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, October 1964. Errata list inserted on p. 154; Check List of Bibliographical Scholarship (pp. 292-302) omitted. 568 copies. Electronic edition: see 1997.3.
  - (1951-52). Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1951. [14], 237 pp., 4
    "Volume Four of the Society's Papers,
    , was produced at the University of Virginia Press under the supervision of Robert L. Morris. All machine and hand composition was done by Mark Rinker, foreman of the composing room. Presswork by William Travis. The half-tones are the work of the Pontiac Engraving and Electrotype Company of Chicago and of the Lynchburg Engraving Co. L. H. Jenkins, Inc. of Richmond did the binding. One thousand copies were manufactured." Reprint: Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, May 1966. Glassine dust jacket. Preliminary advertisements omitted; other preliminary matter and colophon printed on three pages following p. 237; Check List of Bibliographical Scholarship (pp. 217-235) omitted; portions of pp. 217 and 235 combined on new page "217/235"; Stevenson Addendum from p. 235 printed on p. 91. 523 copies. Electronic edition: see 1997.3.
  - (1952-53). Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. [12], 230, [5] pp., 5
    "Volume Five of the Society's Papers, STUDIES IN BIBLIOGRAPHY, was designed, composed and printed by the William Byrd Press, Inc., of Richmond, Virginia. The engravings were made by the Royal Engraving Company of Richmond, Virginia. The text stock is Strathmore Pastelle and the paper used on the covers is Tweedweave Text." Reprint: Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, October 1964. Preliminary advertisements and publications list, Check List of Bibliographical Scholarship (pp. 211-228), and business information (p. 231) omitted. 566 copies. Electronic edition: see 1997.3.
  - (1954). Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1953. [4], 288, [5] pp., 6
    "Volume Six of the Society's Papers, STUDIES IN BIBLIOGRAPHY, was designed, composed and printed by the William Byrd Press, Inc., of Richmond, Virginia. The text is set in Linotype, and Monotype Granjon, display in Monotype Garamont. Text stock is Strathmore Pastelle. The engravings were made by the Royal Engraving Company of Richmond, Virginia, and the books were bound by Charles H. Bohn Company, of N.Y." Reprint: Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, April 1965. Gaskell Addendum from p. 286 moved to p. 266; Check List of Bibliographical Scholarship (pp. 266-286) and business information (p. 289) omitted. 500 copies. Electronic edition: see 1997.3.
  - (1955). Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1955. [4], 240, [4] pp., 7
    "Volume Seven of the Society's Papers, STUDIES IN BIBLIOGRAPHY, was designed, composed and printed by the William Byrd Press, Inc., of Richmond, Virginia. The binding was done by Charles H. Bohn of New York City. The engravings were made by the Royal Engraving Company of Richmond, Virginia and offset inserts were produced by the University of Virginia Press of Charlottesville, Virginia. The type is Granjon and Garamont, the text stock is Strathmore Pastelle." Reprint: Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, April 1965. Check List of Bibliographical Scholarship (pp. 219-238) and business information (p. 241) omitted. 511 copies. Electronic edition: see 1996.3, 1997.3.
  - (1956). Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1956. [4], 275, [1] pp., 8
    "Volume Eight of the Society's Papers,
    , was designed, composed and printed by the William Byrd Press, Inc., of Richmond, Virginia. The binding was done by Charles H. Bohn of New York City. The engravings were made by the Royal Engraving Company of Richmond, Virginia. The type is Granjon and Garamont, the text stock is Strathmore Pastelle." Reprint: Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, April 1965. Check List of Bibliographical Scholarship (pp. 250-267) and business information (p. 273) omitted; Bowers Addendum from pp. 267-269 reformatted on pp. 267-268; errata listed on p. 266 of vol. 9 incorporated on pp. 170-183. 506 copies. Electronic edition: see 1997.3.
  - (1957). Fredson Bowers, Editor. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1957. [6], 273, [1] pp., 9
    "Volume Nine of the Society's Papers,
    , was produced at the University of Virginia Press. Linotype, Baskerville 11, 10, and 8 point, leaded, was employed. Headings were set in 18 point Kennerley. The volume was bound by Charles H. Bohn of New York City. One thousand copies were manufactured on Strathmore Pastelle text stock." Reprint: Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and University Press of Virginia, April 1965. Errata list on p. 266 removed, and its corrections incorporated in reprint vol. 8.; business information (p. 271) and list of available publications (pp. 272-273) omitted. 482 copies. Electronic edition: see 1997.3.
  - (1957); Decennial Extra Volume; also issued as Rudolph Hirsch, Howell J. Heaney, Fredson Bowers, and Lucy Clark, Selective Check Lists of Bibliographical Scholarship, 1949-1955. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1957. viii, 192 pp., 10
    Lists that originally appeared in